<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hereafter folowe x. certayne places of scrypture, by whome it is proued that the doctrynes and tradycyons of men ought to be auoyded</title>
            <title>Bible. English. Selections. 1533.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1533</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16121</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3034.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3206</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33143155</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33143155</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28265</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16121)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28265)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1872:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hereafter folowe x. certayne places of scrypture, by whome it is proued that the doctrynes and tradycyons of men ought to be auoyded</title>
                  <title>Bible. English. Selections. 1533.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 [i.e. 46], [3] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted be [sic] me Robert Wyer dwellynge in saynt Martyns parysshe besyde Charynge Crosse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1553?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Pages numbered on recto only.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: signatures A²⁻³ lacking.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: John Rylands University Library of Manchester.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  English. --  Selections --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28265:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28265:1"/>
            <p>¶Hereafter fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe .x. certayne Places of Scrypture, by whome it is proued, that the doctrynes and tradycyons of men, ought to be auoyded.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Wyer, featuring John the Evangelist (McKerrow 67β)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28265:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:28265:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:28265:3"/>
            <head>The contentes of this boke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>¶The fyrſt place is Deuteronomii / the .iiii. chapytre, where Moyſes ſayth.</item>
               <item>¶The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de place / is of Eſaie the .xxix chapytre / whiche place chryſte.</item>
               <item>¶The thyrde place is / of Mathew, the .xv. chapytre / whiche ſayth.</item>
               <item>¶The fourthe place is / of Paule, in the i. pyſtle / the .iiii. chapytre to Thymothe.</item>
               <item>¶The fyfth place is / of Plaule in the .ii. chapytre / to the Colloſſyans.</item>
               <item>¶The ſyxte place is alſo of Paule in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. i. chapytre / to the Galathyans.</item>
               <item>¶The ſeuenth place is of Paule / in the fyrſte chapytre / to Thymothe.</item>
               <item>¶The eyght place is of ſaynt Peter / in the .ii. chapytre / of his laſt pyſtle.</item>
               <item>¶The nynth place is / of Mathew in the xxiiii. chapytre / whan ſayth he.</item>
               <item>¶The tenth place is / of Salomon in the xxx. chapytre / of his Prouerbes.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="6 pages">
               <desc>〈6 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:28265:3"/>
               <p>ſtes wordes we myght alwaye frely vſe them. ¶Thyrdlye, this errour is alſo by this reproued, that the Papyſtes ſounde forth with full mouthes, that is, that the Churche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnder payne of deed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſynne to be neceſſarye, that we ſhulde faſte in .iiii. tymes of the yere, in the euys of the apoſtels, and certayne other ſayntꝭ all whiche thynges this ſayeng of chryſte confoundeth. ¶What ſoeuer entryth in through the mouth defyleth not the man. Veryly, faſtynge ought to be fre and vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luntarye, ſo that without choſe of dayes or meates euery man after his appetyte, ſhulde faſte or not faſte. ¶Fourthly, the Bn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dictynes, the Bernardynes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſyans, and all other, whiche for mens Tradycyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s abſtayne from egges, fleſſhe and ſuch lyke repugne as aduerſaryes to chryſte. For why theyr doctryne contrary<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth Chryſtes doctryne / after this maner. What ſoeuer entryth in through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth defoyleth, by whiche ſayeng they reproue Chryſte as a lyar, whiche ſayth. what ſo euer entryth in through the mouthe defoy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyth
<pb facs="tcp:28265:4"/> not. And ſo thou mayſte perceyue by this ſayeng of Chryſte that all the ſectes of Monkes. yea &amp; all that hole ſpyrytuall ordynauncꝭ (as they call it) are dyſtroyed &amp; condempned. For yf that, that entryth through the mouth defoyleth not the man howe moche leſſe than, ſhall the thynges / whiche couer the bodye, as the cowle, the coote, the ſhert, the hoſe, the ſhoo, the gow<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, the cloke, grene coloure, yelowe, redde whyte / dyuers colour, beſyde this, the pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, the temple, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> howſe, the cell, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chambre defoyle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man? By this it foloweth that they agayne reproue Chryſt of a lye / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che holde it for ſynne, yf a monke be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed beſyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of his ordre. Veryly what chryſt reakenyth for no ſynne, that boldly affyrme they to be ſynne. What o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynge therfore I praye you is that, that this ſorte of men do, than to ſaye to chryſte. Yea, euyn at his face? thou lyeſt chryſte. For therin is ſynne, wherin thou ſeyſt that none is. Neyther veryly ſhall it any thynge auayle them although they lay forthe for them Gregory, Bernarde,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:28265:4"/> Benedicte, or Frauncys. For we ſhulde more attende to Chryſtes ſayenges, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che onely in the mounte of Thabor was created a teacher by his heuenly father, as Mathew teſtyfyeth in his .xvii. chapytre This is (ſayth he) my dere beloued ſone / in whom I haue delyte, hem here ye. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryly the father ſayd not in this place, here Bernarde, bn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicte, frauncꝭ / but this, this, this, my welbeloued ſone here ye. Ferther more who knoweth whether theſe holye men in theſe doyngꝭ wrought well, or of fendyd. For vndoutedlye they obſerued theſe thynges without conpulſyon, or els for ſome precept, now yf they ſo obſerued them / they are not yet ſo moche to be folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed that Chryſte ſhulde vtterly be forſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken all theſe thynges Chryſte in the ſame chapytre of Mathewe confyrmeth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayeng that foloweth. That (ſaythe he) whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth forth from the mouthe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foyleth the man. For by it all yll adfectes breke forth from the herte, as bawdry, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoultrye, thefte, leſynges, backebytyngꝭ, &amp; ſuche lyke / theſe thynges defyle a man.
<pb facs="tcp:28265:5"/> Here I aſke (for as moche as that is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſynne, whiche wellyth from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> herte, as Chryſte playnly concludeth) by what me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>anes doth butter, chefe, mylke, egges defy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le a man / whyle they come not forth from the mouth, but from the Cowes wombe / and from the henne? what man (I praye you) euer ſawe fleſſhe, ſhauynges (which they call the preeſtes crownes) places, hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry garmentes procede from the mouthe? The kyen perchaunce ſynne whyle they brynge vs forthe mylke, butter, &amp; calues. Moreouer the dreames and Imagynacy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons of monkes, yea and all the humayne tradycyons of maner of lyfe, of clothes, of places / and of all ſuche outwarde thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges not onely derogateth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of god / and deceyue the people / but alſo are lyke to the tryfelynge mowes / and lyghtcaſtꝭ of tomlyng apes. Neuertheleſſe of trueth ſome man couyteth to haue deyntye fare, and to weare fyne and ryche clothes / but this deſyre and appetyte procedeth from the herte. And ſome man can as gready<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eate fyſſhe as fleſſhe. A man ſhall alſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:28265:5"/> fynde ſome that wyll be as prowde in a cote of yelowe clothe, as another wyll be in a cote of ſylke, in concluſyon. Chryſte deceyuyth vs not whan he ſayth. What<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer entryth through the mouthe pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyth not a man / but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth forthe from the mouthe defyleth the man. Nowe yf it be trewe that a man is not defoyled nor ſynneth in ſettynge aſyde the humay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne tradycyons, it muſt nedes folowe that no man is made cleane or deſeruyth any thynge yf he kepe and obſerue them ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally whyle that is onely cleane and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of rewarde, whiche is contrary to ſyn &amp; fylthynes. Wherfore in all the hole lyfe of monkꝭ, there is nothyng pure nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of rewarde, whiche thynge Chryſte al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo affyrmeth by Mathew, the .xv. chapy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre. In vayne (ſayth he) worſhip they me with the tradycyons of men. Why ſaythe he in vayne? veryly for that that in not regardynge thoſe tradycyons nothyng is ſynned, and in obſeruynge them nothyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge is deſerued, for ſurely they are but mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne thyngꝭ, and by this the ſpyrytulte ſut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telly
<pb facs="tcp:28265:6"/> deceyue them ſelf, whyle they reaken a rewarde where none is, &amp; ſuppoſe that they offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de where no ſynne can be ſo that this ſayenge of the Prophete / in the .xiii. Pſalme may very well agre with theyr actꝭ. They feare (ſayth he) where nothyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge is to be feared.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The fourthe place is / of Paule in his fyrſte pyſtle / the 4 chapytre.</head>
               <p>THe fourth place is / of Paule in his fyrſt pyſtle / the .iiii. chapyt<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> to Thy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mothe. The ſpyryte (ſaythe he) ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyth euydentlye, that in the later tymes ſome ſhall departe from the fayth, &amp; ſhall gyue hede to ſpyrytes of errour and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyllyſſhe doctryne, whiche are falſe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers through fayned ſhowe of holyneſſe hauynge theyr conſcyences marked with a hote yron, forbydynge to mary and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundynge to abſteyne fro meates, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che god hathe created to be receyued with thankes gyuynge, of them whiche beleue and haue knowen the treuth, that what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer god creatyd is good, and nothyng to be refuſed, ſo that it be receyued with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:28265:6"/> gyuynge thankes for it, is ſanctyfyed by the worde of god and prayer / of theſe yf thou ſhalte gyue knowlege and counſell to the bretherne / thou ſhalte than ſhowe thy ſelfe a good mynyſter of Chryſte, as one broughte vp in the wordes of faythe and good doctryne / whiche doctryne thou haſte at all tymes folowed. But caſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye from the vnghoſtly &amp; olde wyues fables. O immortall god, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> howe great ſounde of wordes / euyn as it were with thondre. Dothe the apoſtell inuade and ouerthrowe the workꝭ, doctrynes, &amp; ſectes of men. Fyrſte whyle theſe tradycyona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes here after ſhall take pryde that they haue receyued theyr tradycyons of the Pope and other holy fathers. What iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement (I pray you) ſhall Chryſte gyue vpon this mater? Shall he not ſaye on this maner? Paule was my apoſtell and choſen veſſyll (as Luke lefte it mencyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in thapoſtels actes). Why than gaue ye not more credence to them than to the Pope &amp; the fathers / ſeynge that ye haue no ſuertye whether they be the inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:28265:7"/> of god or of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll? What ſhall they anſwere than trowe ye? ¶Secondarely, I aſke theſe tradycionaries, whether that egges, butter, cheſe, mylke, fleſſhe, &amp; other meates / fro whiche they abſtayne on faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyngdayes &amp; by theyr ordres / be the good creatures of god? Whiche yf they wyll graunt (other wyſe wyll they not dare ſaye) than are they vndoutedly euyn the ſame / of whome thapoſtell ſpeketh, that is. That they ſhulde forbyde meates whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che god hath creatyd for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of the true beleuers / that they alſo ſhulde forbyde to mary. And ſo yet ſhall they not wynne out / but ſhall be twyched ſomwhat more on the quycke with this texte of Paule. Nowe harke what Paule ſaythe of them and by what faſſyons he rolleth them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one place to another. ¶Fyrſt (ſaythe he) they are departed from the faythe. For it were impoſſyble for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to teche the ryght wyſenes of workes, oneles they rekened the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe therby to be iuſtyfyed. And this Synyon of theyrs is a very ſure token y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are departed from the faythe. For
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:28265:7"/> they applye, iuſtefyenge to workes / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che iuſtyfyenge ſhulde be gyuen onely to faythe. ¶Secondarely, they gyue hede to ſpirytes of errour, (he ſayeth not to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of errour) but to ſpirytes, that is. That they boſte them ſelfe of ſpirytualytie / re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyſynge to be called ſpirytuall. And ſay that all theyr actes are done, by the ayde and mayntenaunce of the ſpiryte. But whyle they ar bareyne of fayth / it can no otherwyſe be, but that they be blynded in ſpirytuall thynges. Theſe two therfore folowe on the other, to departe from the faythe / and to gyue hede to ſpirytes of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and diſceyte. ¶Thyrdly, thapoſtell ſaythe / that theyr doctryne ſpryngeth of the deuyll theyr authour / whiche thynge muſt alſo nedes folowe. For veryly whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re faythe and the doctryne of Chryſte is not / there Satanas the wonderfull wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keman of ſuche thynges, leadeth theſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronyous ſpirytes with paynted doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and wordes / ſo blyndly, madly, and prowdly, that they reaken them ſelfes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyn the moſt ſpirytuall men. But for as
<pb facs="tcp:28265:8"/> moch as that doctryne ſpryngeth not out of the ſcryptures / it can not be otherwyſe named but deuelyſſhe doctryn. ¶Fourth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, they are falſe ſpekers / for they peruerte holy ſcrypture &amp; the ſayenges of fathers to theyr owne ymagynacyons and drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, as we dayly ſe. That they peruerte ſcrypture, it is euydent by this. For theyr doctrynes &amp; holy ſcryptures in nothynge agree. ¶Fyftly, theyr lyuynge is very hypocryſye / whiche thynge is ſo clere and opyn, that it neadeth no interpretacyon: what is theyr hoole lyfe, but a monſter &amp; hypocryſye in outwarde thyngꝭ / as mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; clothes. ¶Syxtly, they haue theyr conſcyence marked with a hote yron, that is / theyr conſcyence is clene alyenat from the humayne nature. For of truthe other reken they ſynne &amp; are grudgyd in theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence where no parte (as we ſayd be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore) of ſynne can be / euyn as we percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the prynte or marke of one wounde in the body, farre vnlyke other corrupte fuy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters. ¶Seuenthly, they forbed to mary &amp; that is bycauſe they wolde brynge ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:28265:8"/> in to theyr peruerſe ſtate of theyr rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyon, as we daylye ſe bothe preeſtes and monkes, chanons, and freres, leade that lyfe moſt impurely. Wherfore dylygently away and loke for the iudgement of god vpon ſuche doctrynes and ſuch maner of lyfe. As vpon doctrynes whiche ſprynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl erronyous / falſe without faith and full of hypocryſye. Good lorde what man wyll contynewe in that lyfe, and applye to ſuche doctrynes, ſyns god thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth ſo fearefull iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpon them? It ſhall make no matter with howe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vowes a man promyſe theſe doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for the more ſtrayte vowe and othe, that in this behalfe ſhall be made, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more ſoone ſhulde it be broken of &amp; let at large. For that that it was made by the deuyll, and agayne god. But harke, how crafte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they go aboute to vnfolde them ſelfes from this knot, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſferrynge this ſaynge of Paule to the tatyans heretykes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che vtterly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempne matrymony. But ſurelye Paule ſpekyth not here of theym, whiche vtterly condempne matrymony.
<pb facs="tcp:28265:9"/> but of thoſe whiche vnder a maner of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynes, and to ſeme the more holy forbede to mary. But be it, that theſe wordes we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſpoken agayne the tatyans, may they not therfore alſo be ſpoken by the Pope? Yes moſte of all, for yf the pope do thoſe thyngꝭ which the tatyans dyd, why than ſhuld not theſe wordꝭ agre with his actꝭ? For ſurely Paule in this place condemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the workes notwithſtandyng the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpecte of the perſon. Nowe he that forbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyth matrymonye (as the ſygnyfyeng of the wordes playnly openyth) is the dyſcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of Satan and his meſſanger. Than for as moche as the Pope workyth lyke workes, it muſte nedes folowe that he &amp; all his hole flocke of Sophyſters, are the dyſciples and meſſanges of the deuyll, or els Paule lyeth. ¶Eyghtly, many dayes they forbede to eate certayne meates: whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che god hathe created to be receyued with gyuynge thankes. Where agayne thou mayſt ſe the tradycyons of men to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to Satan euyn by god thorow the ſayeng of Paule, as through goddes In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtument.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:28265:9"/> Tell on (I praye you) what mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re what more abhomynable thynge can thou here of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> humayne tradycyons than that they departe fro the fayth, erronyous falſe, deuyllyſhe / and full of hypocryſye. And yf this one place be not ſuffycyent to confounde the doctrynes of men, what than ſhall ſuffyce? Moreouer yf theſe tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycyons of abſtaynynge from meates be deuyllyſhe &amp; fer from a chryſten acte, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doutedly the tradycyons of clothes, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynges, places and other outwarde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſacyons are alſo euyn as nye kynne to the deuyll &amp; as fer from the trewe fayth of chryſte. But here agayne they wyll an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere and ſay that Paule dyd ſpeke theſe wordes by the manychees. Yet ſhall they not ſo eſcape. For Paule in this place ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyth of them, whiche forbede to eate mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, whiche thynge the pope &amp; his doynge. Nowe whether thou call y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope a tatyan or a manyche, I force not. Veryly the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpekyth here agayne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worke, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the pope is gylty in. Ferthermore this place very well appertayneth to theym.
<pb facs="tcp:28265:10"/> For yf a man wolde forbede the eatynge of thoſe meates to morowe, or .ii. dayes fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowynge, ſhulde not this place ſerue hym well, al though he were not named a ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyche? For ſhuld a man lawfully by that meanes do this thynge whiche Paule he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re forbedyth, and ſaye that theſe wordes were not ment by hym, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> olde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nychees? God forbede, but whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe and his monkꝭ, and preeſtes be many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees or not, that refer I to other mens iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gementes. Howbeit I wyll this fer not feare to ſay, that he ſo moche contraryeth Paules doctryne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I can ſcarſely know whether any manyche haue more contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed it or not. ¶Nynethly, they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull. For god hath created meates for that entent (as Paule ſayth) that they ſhuld be receyued with gyuynge thankes Nowe they for this purpoſe gyue in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement to abſteyne fro them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god ſhuld not be lawded for the receyuyng of them. The well and orygynall of al, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che thynges is Infydelyte, and lacke of the trewth of god. For the apoſtle ſaythe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:28265:10"/> that thoſe meates were created for theym that trewely byleue &amp; knowe the trewth that they ſhuld receyue them with gyuyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge thankes. And nowe for as moche as they be falſe byleuers &amp; ignoraunt of the treweth (as thapoſtle in this place callyth them) vndoutedly they are alſo hethens, fer fro chryſten men, blynde and without trewe knowlege. So this is the Elogye of the pope, preſtes, and monkes, whiche is gyuen to them by Paule. ¶Tenthly, They are myſcheuous and peryllous my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſters, whiche in the ſame place of Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le is proued, where he ſayth that Thymo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the is a trew mynyſter and noryſſhed vp in the wordes of fayth, and good doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Yf he ſhall ſhewe theſe thynges to the brethrene. Nowe of the other parte, they without doute are falſe mynyſters, and broughte vp in wordes of falſe byleue &amp; peruerſe doctryne, whiche teche clene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctryne of Paule. ¶Eleue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the apoſtle callyth theyr doctrynes vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghoſtly and tryfelynge fables, than whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I pray you what can be ſayd more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>temptely,
<pb facs="tcp:28265:11"/> that ſo many doctours ſhuld be ſo occupyed aboute ſuche tryfles, whiche the olde wyues are wonte to ſporte them ſelfes with, whan they were gatheryd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther to theyr butteryd cakes, to theyr clenſyng bolles, or to theyr waſſynge ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. And that theyr doctryne are vnghoſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, lyes, and fer from any holynes, altho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ughe they boſte that they were wryten by the ayde &amp; cauſe of the holy ghoſte. What man euer herde the humayne tradycyons ſo erneſtly ſpoken agayne and rebuked, For that that they be bareyne of faythe, hethenyſſhe erronyous, deuyllyſſhe, falſe, counterfayted deuourers of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyences contrarye to the glorye of god, and his creatures, pernycyous fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and olde wyues lyes, Let hym nowe that can auoyde ſo fearefull Iugement of god auoyde it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The fyfth place / is of Paule in the ſeconde chapytre.</head>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:28265:11"/>
               <p>THe fyfte place, is of Paule in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>conde chapytre, to the Colloſſyans Let no man (ſayth he) trouble your conſcyence for meate and drynke, or for a pece of a holy day, as the holy daye of the newe moone or of the ſaboth day, whiche ar but ſhodowes of thynges to come / but the body is of chryſte. Let no man myſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye you from the trewe pathe, whiche af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his owne Imagynacyon walketh in the humbleneſſe and holynes of Angles, thynges, whiche he neuer ſawe vaynely blowen vp with his carnall mynde not holdynge the hede of whom all the bodye by ioyntes and couples takyth noryſſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and is knyt togyther, and groweth with the encreaſynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from god Wherfore yf ye be deed with chryſte from the doctrynes of the worlde, why than as though ye yet lyued in the worlde are ye led with the tradycyons of them, that ſay towche not, taſt not, handle not, all whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che peryſſhe with the abuſynge of them, after preceptꝭ and doctrynes of men, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che thynges veryly haue the ſymylytude
<pb facs="tcp:28265:12"/> of wyſdom by choſen holynes / and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes of the mynde, and weykynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, &amp; not by any worſhyp for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſſhe to his nede. Spekyth Paule nowe agayne of the Manychees? and Tatyans. Or can any man excuſe the Papyſtes of thyſe ſayeng? No, for the apoſtle ſpekyth here of thoſe that entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle the wretchyd conſcyencꝭ with humay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne preceptes and doctrynes that they cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe them to dyſcerne meate fro meate, dryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke fro drynke, cloth fro clothe, &amp; other out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde thynges. Nowe it is openly kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen that the Pope, preeſtes, and monkꝭ, do theſe thynges. For it is ordayned by theyr Decrees, that certayne dayes men ſhulde abſtayne from fleſſhe, egges, but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, cheſe, mylke, &amp; other creatures of god. And they haue alſo for them ſelfes pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyer garmentes faſcyoned fer from other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, agayne all whiche thynges Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le boldly fyghteth. Fyrſte whan he ſayth let no man trouble your conſcyences for meate, drynke, cloth, or day. Whiche thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge what is it other (I praye you) than to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:28265:12"/> ſaye. Be ye not preeſtes, monkes, freers, neyther obſerue ye the popes Decretals, nor byleue ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to be ſynne whiche he cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth and holdeth for ſynne. Now here a man maye perceyue that god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by Paule his electe veſſell that we ſhuld not regarde the Decrees of the pope preeſtꝭ, monkꝭ, &amp; freers, or at leſt way we ſhulde reaken them to be free, &amp; take them as meane thyngꝭ, whiche of them ſelfe be nor expedyent nor preiudycyall, leſt hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pely they myght trouble and ſtere our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcyences. Yf we take not good hede / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thyng is no other to ſay / but be ye not preeſtes, monkꝭ, nor freers. And they that all ready haue entred in to the Papyſtes holy relygyon, ſhuld eyther ryd them ſelfe from it, or this wyſe obſerue the papyſtes Decretals, that yf at any tyme they lette paſſe or tranſgreſſe in any of them, they ſhuld not reaken it to be ſynne, but cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te them as lawfully to be let ſlypped as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned. For all though theſe wordes we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſpoken by the Iewes, whiche obſerued them after the lawe of Moyſes (and Pau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le
<pb facs="tcp:28265:13"/> here ſaith that they were but ſhadowes and fygures of thynges to come, but the body is in chryſte.) Yet neuertheleſſe they moche more agre with the decrees of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, preeſtꝭ, &amp; monkꝭ. For yf that be ſeſſyd whiche god Inſtytuted, and ſhuld nomo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re bynde the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence. Howe moche more than ought nothynge to be Inſtytuted &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded by men, whiche myght byn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence? Whiche thynge hereafter ſhalbe more playnly ſhewed. ¶Seconda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rylye, Paule ſaythe, let no man defraude you, or malycyouſly ſhewe you a wrong marke, to lede you fro the trewe prycke, &amp; begyle you of the rewarde, as who wold ſay. Take hede to your ſelfe that no man myſguyde you from fayth (whiche is the onelye waye to purchaſe the rewarde of helthe) in to the truſte of workes, that ye ſhulde wyll to be Iuſtyfyed, and attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to the reward of helth by a meane whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che the Papyſtes haue preſcrybed. What way and meane they haue preſcrybed. ye ſhall nowe openly perceyue by that, that foloweth. ¶Thyrdely, he ſaythe, let no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:28265:13"/> man deceyue you in voluntary and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen humblenes and holynes of aungels. Peynteth not Paule here, euyn w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr coloures the ſectes of monkes and all the Popes holy flocke? Countyth not the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe and all the papyſtes all theyr beluyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, rorynges, and cryengꝭ in the temple, and theyr obedyence of beckꝭ &amp; duegardes euyn for the hyeſt vertues and workes? So this is the honourable and deuoute humble holyneſſe of the Papyſtes. But nowe of whom had they theyr preceptes and tradycyons? They them ſelfes haue choſen them, and haue ſoughte theym out euyn for theyr owne myſchefes. For by this meanes they haue withdrawen them ſelf from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune humblenes and obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyence of men, of whiche thynges we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue by goddes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one ſhulde ſubmyt hym ſelfe agayne the other, &amp; the one ſhuld obaye the other, whiche thynge they neuer do. For they ar not ſubiecte to a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall ruler (to whom Paule co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to obaye) but haue ſhaken them ſelfe from that yoke, &amp; haue begon a peculyer
<pb facs="tcp:28265:14"/> obedyence and humblenes of theyr owne Inuencyons, neuertheles they boſte that theyr obedyence (in whiche are many ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mefull thynges) fer excellyth the obedyen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of the laye men. Yea &amp; that theyrs is per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyte, &amp; lyke to the obedyence of aungels / whan yet throughout all the hole worlde a man can fynde no ſorte of people more dyſobedye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or blowen vp with more pry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. They haue alſo auowed chaſtyte, and pouerte, neyther labour they as other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do, but after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of heuenly aungels they laude god nyghte and daye in often prayers and ſonges. And to be ſhort they wolde haue men thynke that they lede a heuenly lyfe, whan yet no man is more gylty of horryble pleaſures, no man more ryche in Iniquyte: no man leſſe truely ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, no man more proude herted than they whiche name them ſelfe ſpyrytuall. Yet tranſfer they vnder colour of theyr ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly lyfe, the prycke of faythe from all mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men / and dyſceyue them vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe and Iuſtyfyeng of workes. All theſe thyngꝭ (as I geſſe) were not ſpoken one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:28265:14"/> by the Manychees, and Tatyans, but alſo by the papyſtes, whiche thyngꝭ theyr workes full well declare. ¶Fourthlye, walkynge (ſayth he) in thynges whiche he neuer ſawe, whiche thynge is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uycions in the humane doctrynes &amp; faſcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of lyfe. As who ſayth, that they whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che lyue after thoſe tradycyons, &amp; doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſtycke to no foundacyon nor exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of trewe ſcrypture, neyther are they of any certayntie, whether they doo well or not. For all theyr laboure is vncertayne in ſo moche that yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requyre whether theyr maner of lyf pleaſe god or not, they muſt anſwere. We knowe not, yea &amp; that all theyr good workes be caſt in the wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, and ar of no accompte. Whiche thyng they ar conſtrayned by force to confeſſe. For why, they lacke fayth, whiche fayth onely aſſertayneth vs, that all dedes be acceptable to god, and that without any occaſyon of our deſertes, but onely by the very grace &amp; power of god. So all theyr obedyence and holynes, euyn whan they ſeme beſt, are vncertayne and of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lewe.
<pb facs="tcp:28265:15"/> ¶Fyftely, Vaynely (ſayth he) they are ſwollen with pryde, that is although they can haue no occaſyon of preſumpſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (for they are vnſtable, and falſe bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and lede a curſed lyfe,) Neuertheles yet caſt they vp theyr noſes in the wynde and boſte that theyr maner lyfe is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſte and moſte ſure way to purchaſe helth, ſo ferforth, that they repute all other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes condycyons as vyle and of no valewe, in Regarde of theyr owne. For trewely thoſe wretches perceyue not theyr prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hye carnall mynde, bycauſe of theyr o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermoche angelyke humblenes and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyence. O abhomynable frute of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane doctryne. ¶Syxtly, They ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parte (ſayth he) and varye from chryſte, which is our hed. Truely it is impoſſyble that the tradycyons of men &amp; chryſte ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be in one ſentence. For the one exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyth the other, for yf the conſcyence gyue credence to Chryſte, the truſte of humane tradycyons and workes takyth a fall. But yf the conſcyence put truſte in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, than hath chryſte loſte his place. For
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:28265:15"/> it can not be brought to paſſe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> herte can be grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpon a double fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacion the one muſt nedes fayle, lykewyſe ſe we openly that the Papyſtes truſte onely to theyr cerymonyes &amp; tradycyons, for oon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les they had truſte in theym, truelye they wolde ſette them at nought and forſake them, or els at leſtwaye they wolde vſe them freely, &amp; whan tyme requyred. But yf no ferther daunger were in them, this (Alas) were to moche, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whyle they put truſte in the abhomynablenes of humane doctrynes, they forſake god, and clene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte from hym, whiche thynge Peter al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo teſtyfyeth in his fyrſte pyſtle, in which he dyſcryueth the orders of Monkes with horryble wordes. They are (ſayth he) the ſectes of dampnacyon, whiche denye chry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte, and in the latter pyſtle the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pytre he ſayth on this maner. There ſhal be falſe mynyſters amonge you, whiche ſhall inuent &amp; brynge in dampnable ſectꝭ And ſhall denye the lorde whiche bought them with his blode. ¶Seuenthlye, It may be openly thought by this ſayeng of
<pb facs="tcp:28265:16"/> Paule that our ſpyrytualtie ar twyched in the quycke where he ſayth. Yf ye be ded with Chryſt why than yet ſuffre ye your ſelfes, as thoughe ye were yet lyuynge in the worlde to be troubled and led aboute the buſſhe with humane tradycyons, as thou ſhalte not twyche that, thou ſhalte not eate that, thou ſhalt not handle that, Neyther can any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> denye but that god in this place of Paule forbade to teche &amp; to here the doctrynes of men, yf by them the conſcyence of men ſhulde be bounde &amp; endaungered. Noo man therfore can be with ſalue conſcyence, a monke, a preeſt, a freer, or ſuche lyke. For all they (wyll they or not, are compelled to confeſſe that theyr conſcyences ar entangled and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to the foreſayde tradycyons. A man may perceyue nowe howe effectuall this ſayeng of Paule is agayne the tradycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men. And how horryble it is to be herde that they haue forſaken chryſte whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is our hed: that they haue depted from the fayth, and that they ar made ſo very hethens, whyle yet they ſuppoſe that all
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:28265:16"/> the world hangyth &amp; is maynteyned, tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowly by theyr holyneſſe, whiche is euyn ſo trewe as heuen is vpholden, &amp; ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyth on the ſholders of Atlas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maurytane.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The ſyxte place is / alſo of Paule in the fyrſte chapytre.</head>
               <p>THe ſyxte place is / alſo of Paule in the fyrſt chapytre / to the Galathy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ans. Yf we (ſayth he) or the aungle of heuen teache any other thynge to you than that whiche we haue taught, holde it accurſed as we afore haue ſayd, ſo now ſaye I agayne. Yf any man ſhall teache you any other thynge, than that whiche ye haue receyued &amp; ar lerned of, holde it accurſed. Beholde nowe the Iugement of god vpon the doctrynes of the Pope &amp; other men, that is that ſhulde be accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. But thynke thou not that this curſe is lyke to the papyſtꝭ thretenynges of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munycacions and curſes / but that it is eternall / whiche alſo ſeparateth a man from god, chryſte, helth / and all goodnes,
<pb facs="tcp:28265:17"/> &amp; byndeth hym to Sathanas. O y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Iugement of god. By this therfore it aperyth whether the pope, preeſtes, and monkes can teache any other thynge, or any thynge more than that that chryſte &amp; his apoſtles haue taught. For it is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> afore that chryſt taught after this maner What ſoeuer entryth through the mouthe defyleth not the man, whiche thynge the pope, preeſtes, and monkes openlye Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue ſayeng / Chryſte thou lyeſt. For the Charthuſians ar polluted and dampned for eatynge of fleſſhe. Lykewyſe thynke they that ar lyke to this ſecte. But is not this euyn to ſtryke chryſte in the face and to detecte hym of a lye, to ſpeke yll of hym and to teache an other thynge than euer he taughte? Moreouer this Iugement of perpetuall curſynge is brought, euyn as it ſhulde be, vpon the blaſphemers of the glorye of god, that is, that they ſhulde pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe and be condempned in theyr royall holyneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The .7. place is / of Paule in the fyrſte chapytre.</head>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:28265:17"/>
               <p>THe ſeuenth place is / of Paule in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte chapytre to Thymothe. Tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che them (ſayth he) that they gyue no hede to vntrewe Fables and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes tradycyons, whiche thynges withdrawe from the trueth. Here agayne thou mayſt perceyue how the apoſtle playnly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, that we ſhulde not attende to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes Doctrynes and Decrees ſemyth not this vnto the as a very hell, or at leſt way an occaſyon to dryue the to hell whan Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſayth, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preceptes and tradycyons of men ar fer from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth, yea and they leade a man ſo fer from the trueth that he can not be able to knowe the trewe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſe, but call good yll, and yll good, the day nyght, and the nyght daye. For ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes herte (as we afore haue ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed) can not haue truſte both in chryſtes doctryne, and alſo in the doctrynes &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes of men. For as ſoone as the herte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynneth to applye to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes tradycyons it wexeth ſtraunge to the trueth, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge regardyth it. Of the other parte, after that that the herte begynneth to put
<pb facs="tcp:28265:18"/> hole truſte in chryſte / it can not chuſe but ſet at nought all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes tradycyons. By this thou mayſt ꝑceyue whether the curſe of chryſt, or of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope is more to be feared. The Pope and his complyces, curſe the with theyr cruell exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munycacions euyn to the pyt of helle. Yf thou applye not to theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes. But chryſte thre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenyth and forbedyth the on payne of his euerlaſtyng curſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou gyue no hede to theyr tradycyons &amp; curſes. Now auyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to whiche of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> both thou ſhuldeſt obaye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The eyght Place is / of ſaynt Peter in the .ii. chapytre.</head>
               <p>THe eyght Place is / of ſaynt Peter in the ſeconde chapytre of his laſte pyſtle. There ſhalbe (ſayth he) fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe teachers amonge you, whiche pryuely ſhall brynge in dampnable ſectes, &amp; ſhall denye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde whiche bought them bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge on theyr owne hedes ſwyfte dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pnacyon. And many ſhall folowe theyr poyſonable wayes, by whom the way of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:28265:18"/> treweth ſhall be yll ſpoken of, &amp; throughe couytouſnes ſhall they with fayned wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des make marchaundyſe of you. Here is it playnly openyd why the dyuerſe ſortes of monkes, chanons, and freres / be called dampnable ſectes, veryly for that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they denye chryſte, and falſely lye on the way of treweth. By what meane, ſurely in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> that chryſte ordayned no iuſtyfyeng to be in meate and drynke, clothes, placꝭ, and humane workes / but they ſtyfly affyrme by theyr doctryne and lyuynge that iuſty fyeng, and not iuſtyfyeng reſtyth in tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe thynges. Moreouer chryſte is by theſe wretches inuaded &amp; rebuked of a lye, yea and all the doctryne of chryſte, and fayth is reputed as vyle, and vtterly denayed Yet for all that by theyr gloſynge &amp; payn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted wordes vnder coloure of obedyence, and of the deuyne mynyſters, they haue kepte preuye theyr inſacyable hunger of couytouſnes, and ſo ferforth for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of theyr abhomynable luſtes &amp; wanton pleaſures haue they made mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaundyſe of vs, that they haue almoſte
<pb facs="tcp:28265:19"/> ſhauen the laye people of all theyr goodes and landes euyn with this ſubtyltie, for they booſte &amp; make men byleue that who ſoeuer haue done any benefyte to them, or gyue them any parte of theyr goodꝭ, ſhall deſerue to haue heuen by theyr prayers &amp; cerymonyes. Wherfore al theyr ordynaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and doctrynes ar euyn trewely called of Peter. ſectes of dampnacyon and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemyes of god.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The nynthe Place is / of Mathewe in the .xxiiii. chapytre.</head>
               <p>THe nynth place is / of Mathewe in the .xxiiii. chapytre. Whan (ſaythe he) they ſhall ſay to you. Lo this is Chryſte, byleue them not. For there ſhall aryſe falſe chryſtes, and falſe prophetes, whiche ſhall ſhowe great ſygnes &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, in ſo moche yf it were poſſyble they ſhuld deceyue the very electe. Lo I ſhow all theſe thynges to you. And whan they ſhall ſaye to you. Lo chryſte is in wylder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, go ye not forth, alſo yf they ſhall ſay
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:28265:19"/> to you, chryſt is in the ſecrete placꝭ byleue them not. ¶Nowe ſhowe me I pray you what monke or frete ſhall be ſaued. For euery one rekenyth his helth and ſaluacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be accepted in that place, whiche he byndeth and auoweth hym ſelfe to. And ſayth, here is my chryſte for onles I tary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here, I ſhulde peryſſhe &amp; be dampned. But chryſte anſweryth and ſayth, I am not there, who than ſhall make theſe two ſayenges acorde? Verylye (as I thynke) no man. Wherfore it aperyth by this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng of chryſte, that all doctrynes whiche bynde and dedycate the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence to any place ar clene contrary to chryſt. Now yf chryſte wyll not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the conſcyence be boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to any place, ſurely than of ryght the conſcyence oughte to be free fro meates, drynkes, clothes, tradycyons, and other outwarde thynges. Moreouer for as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as we ſe the Pope and his ſpyritualy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te do this, it is not to be doubted, but this ſayeng of Mathewe makyth extremely agayne them. Ferthermore Chryſte hym ſelfe by this ſayenge ryddeth and aſſoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb facs="tcp:28265:20"/> all preſtes, and monkes, from theyr promyſed vowes for that that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pnyth all ſuche orders and monaſteryes, whan he ſayth, byleue them not. Go ye not thyther. Euen for the ſame purpoſe Luke in his .xvii. chapytre ſayth. The kyngdom of god ſhall not come with the obſeruyng of outwarde rytes and trady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons of men, neyther ſhall it be ſayd. Lo here, lo there. For the kyngdom of god is within you / Is not this ſayeng alſo cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re and effectuall ynoughe to confounde me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes tradycyons?</p>
               <p>¶The doctrynes of men can teache or or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dayne no other thyng but outward thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. Seynge nowe that the kyngdom of god reſtyth not in outwarde thyngꝭ, but in the inwarde, it can no otherwyſe be, but that bothe the teachers and lerners of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes tradycyons (whiche onely teache outwarde thyngꝭ) ar blynde and fer wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de from the prycke of treweth. They ſay we gyue hede and folowe the ſteppes of our holy fathers, which Inſtytuted theſe ordres of monkes, and freres. But they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:28265:20"/> ſhall not eſcape with playeng of that pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunt, for Chryſte pluckyth from them that cloke of falſe colour, whan he ſayth. The choſen men alſo, yf it coulde be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ughte to paſſe, ſhall be led out of the way y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is the electe ſhalbe blynded, but ſhal not contynewe in errour. For there ſhulde no notable errour come (as chryſte hath fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhowed to come) oneles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> electe had erryd and erre. What ſoeuer the doctryne and examples of the holy Fathers be, the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of Chryſte be certayne and playne, to whom therfore we ſhulde more obaye than to the holye Fathers, bycauſe theyr doctrynes and workꝭ be of no certaynte, bycauſe alſo that that, whiche was before ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken maketh agayne theyr tradycyons that is. The kyngdome of god is within you, and not without you, neyther here, nor there?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:28265:21"/>
               <head>¶The tenth Place is / of Salomon the .xxx. chapytre.</head>
               <p>THe tenth Place is / of Salomon in the .xxx. chapytre Of his Prouer bys The wordes of god (ſayth he) are fyred &amp; ar a defence for all them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke to them, and beleue them. Adde thou nothynge to the wordes of hym, left he ponyſſhe the, and left thou be founde cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of a lye. Suffyce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou reader for this tyme with that that hathe ben ſayd, howbeit many other places myghte haue be founde thorowly amonges the prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes whiche wold very wel ſerue this pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe, namelye in Heremye, whiche in his ſeuenth chapytre ſayth. Here ye not that whiche ſemyth ryghtfull and iuſt to you, but that that I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de you. And wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ye in euery waye whiche I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded you, that it myght be well with you. And in the .ix. chapytre, he ſayth by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue forſaken my lawe which I gaue to them, and haue not herde my voyce, nor haue walked in it, but haue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:28265:21"/> gone from it after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frowardnes of theyr hertes, and after Bailym whiche thynge they haue lerned of theyr Fathers. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſayth the Lorde god of the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of Iſraell theſe thynges. Lo I ſhall feade this people with worme wode and gyue them water of gall for theyr drynke and ſhall dyſpercle them amonge nacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s whiche they nor theyr Fathers neuer kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we. And I ſhall ſende my ſwerde after them vntyll they be dyſtroyed. And Eze<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chyell in his .xxxiiii. chapytre, ſayth woo be to the herdes of Iſraell, whiche haue fed them ſelfes. Ar the ſhepe not fed of the herdes? ye haue eaten the mylke, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue coueryd your ſelfe with the wolle, and that that was fatte ye haue ſlayne, but ye haue not fed my flocke. And in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde chapytre of Malachie it is ſayde. And nowe this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement is to you ye preeſtes, yf ye wyll not here, and yf ye wyll not ſette it on your hertes to gyue glory to my name ſayth the Lorde of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacyon. I wyll ſend pouerte vpon you, and I wyll curſe your blyſſynges,
<pb facs="tcp:28265:22"/> and I wyll curſe them bycauſe ye ſette it not in your hertes. Then wyll they crye (as Mycheas ſayth in his thyrde chapyt) to the Lorde, but he ſhall not here them, and he ſhall hyde his face from them at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme, bycauſe they haue wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly led theyr lynes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr owne Inuencyons. And for the myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chefe of thoſe Inuencyons (as O ſee in his .ix. cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pytre wytneſſeth) god ſhall caſte them out of his howſe, and in his .xx. chapytre He ſaythe god ſhall rewarde them af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter theyr way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and after theyr In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uency<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:28265:22"/>
            <p>¶Our lorde ouerthrowe and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke in ſondre euery Inuencyon of perdycyon, and graunte the conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuaunce of his fayth to vs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore vs to the lyght of trewth, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che long tyme hath be derkyd with the clowdes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes tradycyons ſo ferforth that the glorye whiche oughte to be gyuen to the name of god, hathe hytherto ben tranſlated to other names, thorowe falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, and fayned holynes, whiche haue almoſte dyſtroyed the trewe Chryſten fayth.</p>
            <closer>¶Be it refourmed, whan Goddes wyll is. Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:28265:23"/>
            <p>¶Imprynted be me Robert wyer / dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge in ſaynt Martyns paryſſhe beſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de charynge Croſſe.</p>
            <p>¶Cum priuilegio.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28265:23"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of the early blazon or coat of arms of Henry VIII of England, featuring the Order of the Garter, crowned, supported by a dragon and a dog, encircling a shield, Quarterly, three fleurs-de-lys and three lions passant guardant; also a Tudor rose, a fleur-de-lis, a portcullis and an eagle or griffin with crown and sceptre</figDesc>
               <p>· MON · · DIEV · ET · · DROYT ·</p>
               <p>· HONY · · SOYT · QVI · MAL · Y · PENSE ·</p>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:28265:24"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Wyer, featuring John the Evangelist with eagle, and Wyer's name below (McKerrow 68 and 69)</figDesc>
               <head>ROBERT WYER.</head>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:28265:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28265:25"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28265:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
